Finding Aid for William A. Paton Papers 1919-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William A. Paton Papers 1919-1984, 1940-1984
Paton, William Andrew, 1889-.
5.5 linear feet
Professor of accounting at the University of Michigan from 1914 to 1959, consultant and expert witness for court cases, specialist in areas of valuation, utility rates, and income measurement. Transcripts of testimony given in various court cases; correspondence with colleagues and friends, including prominent political and economic conservatives; and topical files containing reports, surveys and teaching materials; also a National Bureau of Economic Research Study (1930) and Salary Amortization Surveys (1919) containing information about the financial organization of various American corporations; and photographs, videotape, and audiotapes.
9583 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by William A. Paton, Jr. (donor 8384 ) in July 1995.
The collection is open for research.
William A. Paton taught accounting at the University of Michigan from 1914 to 1959, and maintained an active interest in his profession until he was well into his nineties. He taught more than 20,000 students over the course of his career.
Paton was born near Calumet, Michigan on July 19, 1889. He was educated at Michigan State Normal College and the University of Michigan, from which he earned his PhD in 1917. Except for the 1916-1917 school year, when he was an economics instructor at the University of Minnesota, Paton spent his entire career on the University of Michigan business school faculty. He also served as a visiting professor at many other universities, including the University of Chicago, the University of California at Berkeley and Harvard.
A prolific writer, Paton published hundreds of articles and book reviews, and was author or co-author of twenty books. Among his best known publications are Accounting Theory, Shirtsleeve Economics, Essentials of Accounting, and Assets-Accounting and Administration. Paton was a political and economic conservative, and his work is informed by a strong belief in free market capitalism, and an equally strong dislike of government regulation.
In addition to teaching, Paton worked as a consultant and expert witness for court cases, federal and state commissions, arbitration hearings and congressional committees. His areas of specialization included valuation, utility rates, and income measurement; he often testified on behalf of utility companies. He also worked for the Bureau of Research and Statistics, the War Trade Board and the Bureau of Internal Revenue.
Paton prided himself on his ability to maintain friendships with former students, including President Gerald R. Ford and many corporate chief executive officers. He kept up an extensive correspondence with hundreds of former students until close to his hundredth birthday, and published the book Words! Combining Fun and Learning at the age of ninety-four. Paton died at Whitehall, Michigan on April 26, 1991.
The William A. Paton papers span the years 1919 to 1984 and mainly document his consulting work, the last two decades of his teaching career, and his post retirement activities. The collection is divided into six series: Testimony; Correspondence; Topical Files; Photographs; Videotape; and Audiotapes.
Subjects:
Accounting.; LeFevre, Robert, 1911-; Libertarians.; National Bureau of Economic Research.; Paton, William A. (William Andrew), 1889-1991; Stans, Maurice H., 1908-1998; Taggart, Herbert F. (Herbert Francis), 1898-1983; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Paton, William A. (William Andrew), 1889-1991; Taggart, Herbert F. (Herbert Francis), 1898-1983; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects-Sound Recordings
Paton, William A. (William Andrew), 1889-1991
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Testimony
  Testimony (2.5 linear ft.; 1925-1969) consists of transcripts of Paton's expert witness testimony for numerous hearings and court cases, as well as correspondence with lawyers and executives.
  - Amalgamated Sugar Co. 1952-1956 (Box 1)
  - American Automobile Association 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - American Electric Power Service Corp. 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - American Power and Light Co. 1943-1948, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Alabama Power Company Case undated (Box 1)
  - Amos-Thompson Corp. 1963 (Box 1)
  - Arkansas Power and Light Co. 1944-1948, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Benton Harbor Malleable Industries 1958-1964 (Box 1)
  - Carter-Colgate Case 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Central Illinois Public Service Co. 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - Champlin Oil and Refining Co. 1958-1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Company of Maryland 1969 (Box 1)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board 1956 (Box 1)
  - Cleveland Electric Illuminating Co. 1946 (Box 1)
  - Consolidated Gas Electric Light and Power Company of Baltimore 1944-1945, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Consumers Power Co. 1948 (Box 1)
  - Continental Casualty Co. 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - COPCO [California and Oregon Power Co.] 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Department of Street Railways 1925-1926 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Federal Communications Commission Hearings 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Federal Taxation 1926-1932 (Box 1)
  - Florida Gas Co. 1963 (Box 1)
  - Fourco Glass Co. 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Fruit Growers Supply Co. 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Gammel v. Ernst and Ernst 1953 (Box 1)
  - General Motors Corp. 1961-1964 (Box 1)
  - Georgia-Pacific 1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Guerdon Industries, Inc. 1961 (Box 2)
  - Houdaille-Hershey Corp. 1945 (Box 2)
  - Illinois Power Co. 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Illinois-Iowa Power Co. 1945 (Box 2)
  - Indiana Telephone Corp. 1956-1968 (Box 2)
  - International Pipe and Ceramics Corp. 1963 (Box 2)
  - J.B. Publishing Co. 1972 (Box 2)
  - Jefferson Standard Life Insurance Co. 1965 (Box 2)
  - Kalman and Pulford Criminal Case 1945 (Box 2)
  - Kelsey-Hayes Co. 1964 (Box 2)
  - Liberty Fund Inc. 1975 (Box 2)
  - Long Island Lighting Co. 1940-1944 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Bell Telephone 1953-1966 (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Accounting Methods 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mississippi Valley Gas Co. 1955-1957 (Box 2)
  - Missouri Water Co. 1954-1958 (Box 2)
  - Mitchell Manufacturing Co. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Mt. Clemens Gas Case 1930 (Box 2)
  - Montana Power Co. 1944-1945, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Northern States Power Co. 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Ohio Bell Telephone Co. 1955-1959 (Box 2)
  - Peoples Gas Light and Coke Co. 1952-1961 (Box 2)
  - Procter and Gamble Co. 1941 (Box 2)
  - Public Service Commission of Maryland 1969 (Box 2)
  - Public Service Electric and Gas Co. 1943-1945 (Box 3)
  - St. Croix Falls 1941 (Box 3)
  - Sperry Rand Corp. 1972 (Box 3)
  - Standard Oil Co. 1973 (Box 3)
  - Tarlow vs. Archbell 1943 (Box 3)
  - Taylor vs. Yerington 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority 1938 (Box 3)
  - Thomascolor, Inc. 1948-1950 (Box 3)
  - Todd Shipyards 1952-1954 (Box 3)
  - Transamerica Corporation 1943-1944, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Trolz and Associates 1956 (Box 3)
  - Union Oil and Gas Corporation of Louisiana 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - United Industrial Corporation 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - United States General Accounting Office 1949-1960 (Box 3)
  - Wayne County Road Commissioners undated (Box 3)
  - West Share Construction Co. 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Wisconsin Public Service Commission 1932, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Wisconsin Screw Company 1958 (Box 3)
  - Wyandotte, Michigan 1932 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (1.25 linear ft.;1947-1983) contains Paton's exchanges with colleagues, friends and former students. The series documents his ideas about issues in the accounting profession, as well as his highly conservative opinions regarding local and national current events. Among Paton's correspondents are Nixon cabinet member Maurice Stans and Libertarian Robert LeFevre.
  - 1947-1978
    - A-H, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - I-Z, 11 folders (Box 4)
  - 1977-1983
    - A-Z, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Greer, Howard 1972-1980 (Box 4)
  - LeFevre, Robert 1961-1978 (Box 4)
  - Shapiro, Harold 1983 (Box 4)
  - Stans, Maurice 1956-1974 (Box 4)
  - Yang, J.M. 1966-1983 (Box 4)
  - Zeff, Stephen A. 1963-1981 (Box 4)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files (1.25 linear ft.; 1919-1984) contains correspondence, articles, reports, surveys and teaching materials. Of particular interest are two studies which Paton carried out early in his career. The National Bureau of Economic Research study (1930), and the Salary Amortization Surveys (1919), which he carried out for the Bureau of Internal Revenue, both provide a glimpse of the financial organization of various American corporations. Biographical information is located in Box 5 of the series.
  - Accountants' Graduate Study Conference 1950 (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor News 1978-1982 (Box 4)
  - Annual Report of Activities 1947-1974 (Box 4)
  - Article Manuscripts undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Association of Certified Public Accountant Examiners 1958 (Box 5)
  - Biographical Information 1944-1991 (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews 1930-1961 (Box 5)
  - Communicating Financial Data Conference 1952 (Box 5)
  - Consumer Credit Conference 1953 (Box 5)
  - Corporate Profits [book], 1965-1975 (Box 5)
  - Detroit Free Press Correspondence 1949-1962 (Box 5)
  - Economic Club of Detroit Speech 1949 (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia Americana 1953-1962 (Box 5)
  - Financial Executive Magazine, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - Foundation for Economic Education Correspondence 1970-1983 (Box 5)
  - Great Lakes Conference of Railroad and Utilities Commissioners 1960 (Box 5)
  - Horton and Daughters Publishing Correspondence 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - "Is Government Indispensable?" undated (Box 5)
  - Klein Decision 1955 (Box 5)
  - Lawrence, Howard-Doctoral Student 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - Letters to the Editor and Jingles 1941-1979 (Box 5)
  - Liberty Fund, Inc. 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research
    - Correspondence with Edwin Gay 1929-1932 (Box 5)
    - Profits Study 1930 (Box 5)
    - Profits Study Data Sheets circa 1930 (Box 5)
  - National Machine Tool Builders' Association 1957 (Box 5)
  - Niehuss, Marvin L. 1961 (Box 5)
  - Ninety-fifth Birthday 1984 (Box 5)
  - Paton Accounting Center 1970-1978 (Box 5)
  - Paton Genealogy 1983 (Box 5)
  - Public Utility Executive Program circa 1950s (Box 5)
  - Republican National Committee 1960 (Box 5)
  - Retirement Scrapbook 1958 (Box 5)
  - Salary Amortization Surveys 1919, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Salary Survey Reports 1919, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Shirtsleeve Economics
    - Book Reviews 1952-1961 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Stevenson, Dean Russell A. 1953-1955 (Box 5)
  - Taylor, Fred Manville biography 1933-1972 (Box 5)
  - Teaching Materials 1954-1965, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Tool and Die Industry 1960 (Box 6)
  - Underground Homes 1962-1980 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan School of Business Administration 1962-1967 (Box 6)
  - University Press of Kentucky 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Ways and Means Committee Statement 1953 (Box 6)
  - Words! Combining Fun and Learning correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Working Capital Study 1932 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  Photographs (4 folders and 1 album; 1922-1984) includes formal portraits of Paton, candid pictures of him at speaking engagements, and group portraits from events at the School of Business Administration and Accountants' meetings.
  - Accounting and Business Administration Groups 1922-1979 (Box 6)
  - Ceremonies and Informal Groups 1950-1978 (Box 6)
  - Class of 1926 circa 1970s (Box 6)
  - Portraits 1965-1984, undated (Box 6)
  - Eighty-fifth Birthday Album 1974 (Box 6)
- Videotape, U-Matic
  Videotape (1 tape; 1973) is an interview of Paton by his colleague Professor Herbert Taggart.
  - WAP interviewed by Professor Herbert Taggart 1973 (Box 6)
- Audiotapes
  Audiotapes (2 tapes; 1968-1969) contains speeches about the effects of inflation.
  - Distinguished Service Award presentation 1968, 5" reel-to-reel tape (Box 6)
  - University of Cincinnati Sesquicentennial speeches 1969, audio cassette (Box 6)